Finding Aid for Industrial Development Division (University of Michigan) records, 1959-1991
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Industrial Development Division (University of Michigan) records 1959-1991
University of Michigan. College of Engineering. Industrial Development Division.
6 linear feet
9740 Bimu 2
Division of the Institute of Science and Technology primarily established to provide a link between higher technology research at the University of Michigan and private industries in the State of Michigan. Transferred into the School of Business Administration and the College of Engineering's Office of Technology Transfer in the late 1980s. The record group documents the administration, history, and projects of the Industrial Development Division and includes five series: Administrative File, Historical File, Projects, Public Relations, and Reports.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were transferred from the Office of Technology Transfer (Donor # 8477 ) in August of 1996.
The records are open to research.
The Industrial Development Division (IDD) was established in 1960 within the Institute of Science and Technology (IST), which had been created the previous year with the broad goal of providing state support for the private industries of Michigan. IDD was charged with two basic initiatives: to determine how science and technology could be utilized more effectively to aid state industry and to assist industry by organizing and implementing programs analogous to those existing state programs which aided agriculture. In fulfilling these missions, IDD played two roles. First, it served as a locus where state industrial, educational, governmental, professional, and civic groups could collaborate in research and organizational activities to better exploit their individual capabilities. Second, it supported and conducted studies to determine the needs of Michigan industries and to develop solutions to these needs through the utilization of new technology.
The products of the work of IDD were several conferences and research publications. As noted in "Fifteen Years, 1960-1974," a short history of IDD (Box 1, Historical Files), the unit engaged in "industry research," different than purely scientific or technological research in that it considers the "interrelations of the business, economic, marketing, financing, employment, legal, and social factors" with the technological solutions it develops. Extensive and widely varied topics of research and conferences included electronics, machine tools, computers, solar energy, manufacturing, the automotive industry, manufacturing, pollution, housing, and management techniques. IDD also performed a consulting function, serving as a liaison between industrial, governmental and academic spheres, which provided information on where answers to technological and economic questions could be found. Finally, through its work, IDD also provided educational and occupational opportunities for graduate students in business administration, law, and engineering, many of whom went on to teach in other institutions, increasing the expansive network of IDD.
In the late 1980s, the programs of IDD were separated and housed within the School of Engineering's Office of Technology Transfer and the School of Business Administration. The Office of Technology Transfer has since been disbanded, and the functions of IDD that were housed there have been incorporated into other parts of the school. As of this writing (January 1997), the Business/Industry Economic Division of IDD still exists within the School of Business Administration.
The records of the Industrial Development Division measure two linear feet and range from 1960 to 1991. These materials provide particularly good documentation of some of the programs and projects run through this unit. The record group is divided into five series: Administrative File, Historical File, Projects, Public Relations, and Reports, and Publications.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. College of Engineering. Industrial Development Division.; Research, Industrial--Michigan.; University of Michigan. Institute of Science and Technology.; University of Michigan. Office of Technology Transfer.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan. School of Business Administration.; Science and Industry--Michigan.; Education, Higher--Research.; Research institutes--Michigan.; Industrial development projects--Michigan.; Industry and education.; University of Michigan--Research.
- Administrative File
  The Administrative File holds the records of various committees within IDD and documentation of various reviews of the unit. "Memoranda and Correspondence" primarily contains departmental communications with other university offices. Records of two Review Committees, 1978 and 1984-1985, pertain to analyses of IDD and its original parent organization, Institute of Science and Technology (IST). These folders hold valuable documentation on the status of IDD at those times. The "Realignment" folders contain materials relating to IDD's administrative shift from IST to the College of Engineering and the School of Business.
  - Dean's Review 1987 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee Memoranda and Meeting Minutes 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - Five Year Plan (Preliminary) 1982 (Box 1)
  - Memoranda and Correspondence (miscellaneous) 1962-1987 (Box 1)
  - Planning Team on Economic and Industrial Development Activity 1987 (Box 1)
  - Realignment 1987-1988
    - Clippings 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    - General Files 1987-1988, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Transition Plan 1988 (Box 1)
  - Review Committee 1978, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Review Committee 1984-1985
    - General (Box 1)
    - Report 1985
- Historical File
  The Historical File contains materials specifically written or compiled to record the history of the department. "Fifteen Years, 1960-1974" and "History, 1975-1978" are bound documents written to allow for evaluation of IDD from a "long-range point of view." The "Clippings" file contains references to IDD and related subjects in both local newspapers and national research journals.
  - Background Notes circa 1973 (Box 1)
  - Brochures (miscellaneous) (Box 1)
  - Clippings 1963-1980 (Box 1)
  - Early History (Box 1)
  - "Fifteen Years 1960-1974" (History of IDD) (Box 1)
  - History 1975-1978
- Projects
  The Projects series consists of documents relating to some of the major programs IDD has initiated. Along with a small number of administrative records, most of the documents in this series are project proposals and status reports of each program. The following subseries hold substantial records. The "Aluminum Study" examined the economic and environmental impacts of the replacement of iron and steel with aluminum in many industries. The "Automotive Community Adjustment Program" attempted to confront problems caused by the loss of jobs in the automotive industry during the late 1970s and early 1980s. The "Innovation Center" was designed to facilitate the transfer of technology developed in academic research laboratories to the commercial sector and to stimulate the formation of small high-technology companies. In the "Mills Study," IDD worked through a grant from the Office of Economic Expansion within the Michigan Department of Commerce to explore the possibility of establishing a mill to recycle scrap iron into steel.
  - Aluminum Study
    - "Impact on Aluminum and Ferrous Industries of Accelerating Substitution of Aluminum for Iron and Steel," 1978 (Box 1)
    - "Preliminary Aluminum Recycling Analysis," 1978 (Box 1)
    - "Phase II Progress Report," 1978 (Box 1)
    - "Phase II Report on the Substitution of Aluminum and Other Lightweight Materials in Automotive Production," 1979 (Box 1)
  - Automotive Community Adjustment Program
    - Flint and Genesee Counties, MI June 1981 (Box 1)
    - Grant Proposal 1980 (Box 1)
    - "Industry, Infrastructure, and Marketing Plan Development," 1980 (Box 1)
    - Planning 1980 (Box 1)
  - Employment Transition Program 1986 (Box 2)
  - Industry Assistance Packet 1984 (Box 2)
  - Innovation Center
    - "An Analysis of the National Science Foundation's Innovation Centers Experiment," 1977 (Box 2)
    - Memoranda 1979-1987 (Box 2)
    - Program Description 1983 (Box 2)
    - Selected Program and Project Outlines 1989 (Box 2)
    - Selected Program and Project Outlines and Budgets 1989 (Box 2)
  - Mills Study
    - "Analysis of Ferrous Scrap availability in Michigan and the Great Lakes Region," 1980 (Box 2)
    - "Analysis of Michigan as the Site for a Small Electric Mill to Recycle Scrap into Steel," 1974 (Box 2)
  - "Overall Program Review," 1960-1985 (Box 2)
  - Program Formulation (Box 2)
  - Solar Energy Seminar 1977 (Box 2)
  - State Technical Services Program 1968 (Box 2)
  - Workshop on Small Bus Product and Market Appraisal, Final Report 1975
- Public Relations
  Public Relations is a small series that includes the "Brag Files," so called because they contain complimentary clippings and correspondence from companies and individuals with whom IDD worked. Similarly, "Testimonial Letters" contains letters thanking IDD and acknowledging the positive effects of the division's efforts.
  - "Brag File," 1968-1992, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Testimonial Letters 1988
- Reports
  The Reports series holds general reports on the affairs of IDD. "Annual Reports" and "Presidents Reports" are annual overviews of the unit submitted to the president of the university and are an excellent source for identifying the activities of IDD in select years. The reports in these two folders cover each academic year between 1967-68 and 1987-88. "Executive Summaries" give short synopses of the division's activities from 1990 to 1991.
  - Activities Report 1985-1986 (Box 2)
  - Annual Reports 1968-1975 (Box 2)
  - Development Cost Study 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - Executive Summaries 1990-1991, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - President's Reports 1967-1988 (Box 2)
  - Special Projects Division 1981-1987 (Box 2)
- Publications
  Publications (4 linear feet, 1959-1990) is divided into two series: "Monographs" and "Studies." "Monographs" (3 linear feet, 1963-1990) are published papers of IDD research findings. The most common topics are research related to how small and medium-sized firms function, the management of industrial firms, the use of computers and other technology in industrial production, predictions for the future of industry in Michigan, and surveys of research on industry that has been conducted nationally and internationally. The monographs are arranged alphabetically by title. "Studies" (1 linear foot, 1959-1988) includes papers prepared for conferences or as part of cooperation between academic and industry research groups. The majority of the papers are analyses of Michigan's automotive industry, as well as steel production and opportunities for growth in Michigan industry.
  - Monographs
    - Anatomy of an Industry: A Study of the Michigan Machine Tool Industry in its National and International Setting, by Bacon et. al. 1963 (Box 3)
    - Anatomy of an Industry: A Summary of Findings and Conclusions from a Study of the Michigan Machine Tool Industry in its National and International Setting, by Bacon et. al. 1963 (Box 3)
    - Computer-Aided Part Programming for Numerical Control: An Industry Study, by McCarroll 1969 (Box 3)
    - Computer-Generated Time Standards, by Steffy and Darby 1968 (Box 3)
    - Computerized Ratio Analysis: An Aid to Decision-Making, by Steffy, Mason and Polacsek 1968 (Box 3)
    - Constraints to the Development and Marketing of Medical Electronic Equipment, by Jones 1969 (Box 3)
    - Directory of Research, Development, and Testing Facilities in Michigan, edited by Rempp 1971 (Box 3)
    - Directory of Research, Development, and Testing Facilities in Michigan 1981 (Box 3)
    - Directory of Research, Development, and Testing Capacity in Michigan 1990 (Box 3)
    - Economic Development Methods and Strategies, edited by Conboy and Oshiro 1989 (Box 3)
    - Economic Guidelines for Justifying Capital Purchases, with Numerical Control Emphasis, by Steffy, Smith and Souter 1973 (Box 3)
    - Electrical Discharge Machining for the 1970s by Quackenbush and Lawrence, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Electric Power Reform: The Alternatives for Michigan, edited by Shaker and Steffy 1976 (Box 3)
    - Electronics in Michigan: A Study of the Electronic Industry in Michigan in its National and International Setting, by Bacon, Jr. and Rempp 1967 (Box 3)
    - Energy: The Impact of Availability and Prices on Future Business Prospects, edited by Peelle 1975 (Box 3)
    - Finance, Entrepreneurship, and Economic Development, by Brophy 1974 (Box 3)
    - Financial Ratio Analysis, An Effective Management Tool, by Steffy, Zearley and Strunk 1974 (Box 3)
    - Financing in Michigan: Research and Development vs. Manufacturing Firms, by Chastain and DeVries 1966 (Box 3)
    - Frontiers in Manufacturing Technology vol. 1, edited by Smith 1966 (Box 3)
    - Frontiers in Manufacturing Technology vol. 2, Numerical Control Today, edited by Smith and Peelle 1967 (Box 3)
    - Frontiers in Manufacturing Technology vol. 3, Machine Tools, Machinability, and Electro-Machining Processes, edited by Smith and DiGiovanni 1968 (Box 3)
    - Frontiers in Manufacturing Technology vol. 4, Numerical Control for Tomorrow, edited by Smith and Peelle 1969 (Box 3)
    - Frontiers in Manufacturing Technology vol. 5, Computer Technology for Today's Manager, edited by Smith and Peelle 1970 (Box 3)
    - Horizons of Industrial Productivity, edited by Jones 1977 (Box 4)
    - Horizons of Industrial Productivity, vol. 2, edited by Fossum 1980 (Box 4)
    - Housing Market Opportunities: Industrialized Housing, New Towns, and Rehabilitation, edited by Bernhardt 1972 (Box 4)
    - Housing: New Trends and Concepts, edited by Bernhardt 1972 (Box 4)
    - The Industrial Engineering Plant Audit, by Steffy and Hawley 1977 (Box 4)
    - Industrial Purchasing Controls for the Small and Medium-Sized Firm, by Steffy, Schultz and Nath 1979 (Box 4)
    - Industrialized Housing, by Pearson 1972 (Box 4)
    - Introduction to Group Technology in Manufacturing and Engineering, by Wilson and Henry 1977 (Box 4)
    - Inventory Control for the Small and Medium Sized Firm: Computer-Aided Inventory Control and Manual Inventory Control Methods, by Steffy, Buer and Schultz 1970 (Box 4)
    - Management Control Systems for Small and Medium-Sized Firms, by Steffy, Berka and Murphy 1975 (Box 4)
    - Management Standards for Computer and Numerical Controls, by Smith and Evans 1977 (Box 4)
    - Manufactured Housing in the 1970s edited by Paraskevopoulos and Smith, 1970 (Box 4)
    - Marketing Bank Services to Business, by Krachenberg 1979 (Box 4)
    - Metalworking Research: A Survey of Metalworking Research in Universities and Institutes in Europe, by Wilson 1965 (Box 4)
    - Metalworking Research: A Survey of Metalworking Research in Universities and Institutes in Japan, by Wilson 1965 (Box 4)
    - Metalworking Research: A Survey of Metalworking Research in Universities and Institutes in the United States, by Wilson 1965 (Box 4)
    - Michigan Economic Development Education Manual, edited by Conboy and Guiles 1979 (Box 4)
    - Michigan's Tool and Die Industry, Technological Change, by Smith 1968 (Box 4)
    - Michigan Water and Air Pollution Standards, by Crockett and Berets 1970 (Box 4)
    - New Jobs in a Clean Environment, edited by Swinyard 1972 (Box 4)
    - Numerical Control: A Bibliography, by Rempp 1968 (Box 4)
    - Numerical Control Justification: A Methodology, by Steffy, Bawol, LaChance and Polacsek 1967 (Box 4)
    - Performance Evaluation Systems, by Steffy and Darby 1969 (Box 5)
    - Planned Innovation: A Dynamic Approach for Selecting, Evaluating, and Guiding Successful Development of New Products, by Facon, Jr. and Butler, Jr. 1973 (Box 5)
    - Planned Innovation: A Dynamic Approach to Strategic Planning and the Successful Development of New Products, second edition, by Bacon, Jr. and Butler, Jr. 1981 (Box 5)
    - Production Control for the Small and Medium-Sized Firms, by Steffy, Bardsley and Shryock 1974 (Box 5)
    - Production Technology Advancements: A Forecast to 1988 by Evans, 1973 (Box 5)
    - Productivity Bargaining: A Study in Contract Construction, by Maloney 1977 (Box 5)
    - Productivity Concepts, by Steffy and Oznal 1981 (Box 5)
    - Productivity and Cost Control for the Small and Medium-Sized Firm, by Steffy, Ahmad and Reyes 1980 (Box 5)
    - Prospects for Oil and Gas from Silurian-Niagaran Trend in Michigan, by Yellig, Jr. and Tek 1976 (Box 5)
    - A Prototype Structural System Integrating Mechanical Services, by Erickson 1969 (Box 5)
    - Reducing Worker Absenteeism, by Jones, Miller and Fossum 1979 (Box 5)
    - Research and Development for Small and Medium Sized Firms, edited by Armstrong 1966 (Box 5)
    - Research Emphasis in Michigan Universities, by Bacon, Jr. and Bayer 1964 (Box 5)
    - Research in Support of Numerical and Adaptive Control in Manufacturing, by Colwell, Frederick and Quackenbush 1969 (Box 5)
    - Retrofitting Machine Tools: Converting Conventional Machine Tools to Numerical Control, by Hardy 1967 (Box 5)
    - The Role of Buyer-Initiated Formal Communication in Marketing Research and Development to the Government, by Rovelstad 1971 (Box 5)
    - Starting a High-Tech Company: An Insider's View of Entrepreneurship, edited by Guiles and Peelle 1985 (Box 5)
    - Strategic and Product Planning for the Auto Industry, edited by Cole 1982 (Box 5)
    - A Technical Survey of the Tool and Die Industry in Michigan, by Schmidt 1967 (Box 5)
    - Technology Transfer, Innovation, and Marketing in Science-oriented Spin-off Firms, by Lamont 1971 (Box 5)
    - The Transformation from Technical Professional to Technical Manager: Special Career Management Concerns, by Hill and Somers 1988 (Box 5)
    - Vacation Housing and Recreation Land Development, edited by Bernhardt 1973 (Box 5)
    - Wetland Utilization for Management of Community Wastewater: Concepts and Operations in Michigan, by Hammer and Kadlec undated (Box 5)
  - Studies
    - The Auto-In-Michigan Project (Box 6)
      - The Impact of U.S. Automotive Trends on the Demand for Machine Tools, by Smith 1986 (Box 6)
      - Innovative Analysis of Michigan's Manufacturing Foundation, by Russell undated (Box 6)
      - Project Report 1985 (Box 6)
      - The Uncertain Future of Michigan's Automotive Stamping Industry, by Smith 1986 (Box 6)
    - Automotive Demand for Galvanized Steel and its Impact on Steel Galvanizing Capacity, by Hervey, Smith and Heytler 1985 (Box 6)
    - Automotive Materials for the 1990s by Hervey and Smith, 1985 (Box 6)
    - Conference on Production Research Abroad 1963 (Box 6)
    - Directory of Black Businesses in Michigan, compiled by Horning and Jackson 1970 (Box 6)
    - Economic Development Administration University Center Final Report 1979-1980 (Box 6)
    - Electronics Research Center of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA)
      - Location Proposal 1963 (Box 6)
      - Endorsements for the Location Proposal 1963 (Box 6)
    - The Feasibility of Establishing Steel Galvanizing or Related Facilities in Michigan, Appendix A: Review of the Literature, by Heytler 1985 (Box 6)
    - Feasibility of a World-Scale Chemicals Complex Supplied with Hydrocarbons from Natural Gas Processing Plants near Kalkaska, Michigan, by Hawley 1977 (Box 6)
    - Future Impact of Automotive Trends on Michigan and U.S. Machine Tool Industry, by Smith 1985 (Box 6)
    - Growth Through New Product Development, by Bacon, Jr. 1963 (Box 6)
    - A Handbook for the Rolling Resistance of Pneumatic Tires, by Clark and Dodge 1979 (Box 6)
    - Industrial Productivity Workshop: Executive Summary 1974 (Box 6)
    - Industrial Productivity Workshop: Executive Summary 1976 (Box 6)
    - An Investigation of Technological Change at the Firm Level (dissertation), by Bacon, Jr. 1965 (Box 6)
    - A Literature Survey of Computer-Based, Cost-Estimation Models for Auto Body Manufacturing, by Park and Heytler 1989 (Box 6)
    - Michigan Business and Economic Research Bibliography July 1970-July 1979, 1981 (Box 6)
    - The Michigan Machine Tool Industry: Preliminary Summary Report 1963 (Box 6)
    - Multivariate Techniques for Marketing Research in Industrial Markets by Bacon 1987 (Box 6)
    - Proceedings of the Michigan Machine Tool Conference, edited by Chastain 1962 (Box 6)
    - Report 0.0 Proposed Plan of Activities Concerning Social, Economic and Organizational Issues 1983 (Box 6)
    - Report 1.0 The Program for the Industrial Technology Institute 1982 (Box 6)
    - Research in Support of Motor Truck Brake Systems Design and Development, by Fancher 1980 (Box 6)
    - Short-and Long-Range Trends in Machine Tool Demand: A Delphi Forecast, by Smith 1978 (Box 6)
    - Subterranean Urban Systems, by Birkerts 1974 (Box 6)
    - A Summary Paper on Automotive Stamping Operations 1986 (Box 6)
    - Toward World Class Manufacture of Automotive Bodies: A Status Report 1988 (Box 6)
    - Willow Run Laboratories Annual Report 1959 (Box 6)
    - Willow Run Laboratories Publications November 1960 through December 1964, 1967 (Box 6)